Okay, welcome back.
We're now going to begin Chapter 3, Principles of Neoplasia.
And the first section in this particular chapter
is actually entitled Neoplasia.
Before we begin, just some basic principles.
The word neoplasia, neo means new, and plasia means growth.
And what's important to recognize concerning neoplasia
is that it is unregulated, irreversible, and monoclonal.
Now these three features are important
because it's these three features,
the fact that the growth is unregulated,
that it's irreversible, and that it's monoclonal.
These three features help to distinguish neoplasia
from hyperplasia or repair.
Now just as an example, hyperplasia, as you'll recall,
occurred when there might be an increase in stress
on an organ.
For example, a woman becomes pregnant,
the uterus, the smooth muscle of the uterine wall
actually undergoes hyperplasia.
However, hyperplasia is regulated.
It's regulated by the physiology of the pregnancy.
It's reversible.
When the woman delivers, her uterus will again shrink down
to normal size, and it's polyclonal.
And by polyclonal, what we mean is that multiple cells
produce daughter cells, which then subsequently results
in the hyperplasia.
Whereas cancer is monoclonal, and we're going to talk
about monoclonality in a moment.
So again, these are three very important features
of neoplasia.
Now as I mentioned just a moment ago,
monoclonal refers to the fact that all the tumor cells
actually arise from one single progenitor cell,
one single mother cell, or one single father cell.
And that's what the term monoclonal means.
So as I've stated here, the neoplastic cells are derived
from a single mother cell.
Clonality can be determined by G6PD isoforms,
and this actually is a very high-yield principle,
which we should probably take a moment to highlight.
So what I'm going to do here is actually just create a whiteboard,
and then spend a moment just explaining what we mean by this.
So let's go back and pretend for a moment that we are looking
at the uterus of a female.
And let's just imagine that this uterus actually is comprised
of four cells.
Now obviously, the female uterus is not made up of four cells,
but we can just imagine just for the purposes of illustration.
One of the important enzymes that is present on the X chromosome
in a female is G6PD.
And I'm going to take a moment to remind you that G6PD is actually
X-linked, and that there are multiple isoforms that exist
across the population.
So for example, there may be a G6PD-A, a G6PD-B, a G6PD-C,
a G6PD-D, etc. There are dozens of isoforms of G6PD.
Now any single female in the population will have only inherited
one copy of G6PD, one isoform of G6PD from their mother,
and one isoform of G6PD from their father.
So let's pretend a woman inherits G6PD-A from the mother
or the father, and G6PD-B from the other parent.
So basically, each of the cells in that female,
because she's got two X chromosomes and G6PD is X-linked,
each of the cells in that female will express both G6PD-A
and G6PD-B.
So for example, if this uterus that we've drawn up here
is actually made up of four cells, then these four cells
would be expressing G6PD-A and B, and each of them
would express the two isoforms because each cell contains
two X chromosomes.
So it would look something like that.
Now the next important concept to bear in mind is that
in a female, one X chromosome is going to be randomly inactivated,
so that in any particular cell there would only be one active
variant of G6PD, and you know that the inactivation of the X
chromosome is actually random.
So for example, if we had these four cells that I've drawn up
here, it may be that in this particular cell, G6PD-B is
inactivated, or that X chromosome is activated.
It may be that in this cell, this X chromosome is inactivated.
It may be that in this cell, this X chromosome is inactivated,
and that in this cell, this X chromosome is inactivated.
Now X chromosome inactivation is going to be random, so that in
the end, if we were to look at all the cells present within the
female's uterus, for example, the ratio of G6PD-A to G6PD-B
would be one to one.
Now, let's just imagine for a moment that a woman develops
hyperplasia of her uterus.
So she becomes pregnant, and the uterine wall undergoes hyperplasia,
and when it undergoes hyperplasia, hyperplasia is defined as an
increase in the number of cells.
So let's say that, for example, this particular cell produces two
daughter cells, and this particular cell produces two daughter cells,
and this cell also produces two daughter cells, and this cell also
produces two daughter cells.
Now, the daughter cells would show the exact same active isoform of G6PD as
their mother cell.
So these two cells would produce G6PD, would be expressing G6PD-A, these two
cells would be expressing G6PD-B, these two cells would express G6PD-A, and these two
cells would express G6PD-B, because obviously the mother cell also expresses G6PD-B.
So in hyperplasia, which is polyclonal, i.e., the cells are derived from multiple
individual cells, the ratio of G6PD-A is going to be maintained, because here we can
see that there are one, two, three, four cells that are expressing G6PD-A, and one, two, three,
four cells that are expressing G6PD-B.
So really, that maintains the one-to-one ratio, and that's exactly what we would expect in
a polyclonal proliferation, i.e., that's what we would expect to see in hyperplasia, that
the one-to-one ratio of G6PD is maintained.
Now let's take another example, and let's go back and draw the exact same scenario.
So again, we've got four cells present within the uterus, and these are the smooth muscle
cells of the uterus, and we said that, you know, this is perhaps expressing G6PD-A, this
one expresses G6PD-B, this one expresses G6PD-A, and this one expresses G6PD-B, so that the
ratio is approximately one-to-one.
Now in the case of neoplasia, all the cells, all the tumor cells, are derived from a single
mother cell.
So for example, if this one particular cell were to become mutated and result in neoplasia,
then what would happen is that one cell would actually produce all of the tumor cells.
And so all of the tumor cells would actually all express G6PD-A.
And so it's this concept that one cell produces all the tumor cells that is actually the idea
behind monoclonality, i.e., there is one mother cell that's producing all these baby cells.
And the way by which we can prove monoclonality in a female would be to look at G6PD isoforms.
And so if we see that the tumor is composed of one isoform of G6PD, then that would indicate
that we're dealing with a monoclonal proliferation, hence we're dealing with neoplasia.
Whereas if we saw that the G6PD isoforms were expressed in a roughly one-to-one ratio, then
we would know that we're actually dealing with a polyclonal proliferation, which would
basically be hyperplasia.
So I hope that that's clear, because that's a very high-yield concept that shows up on
examinations.
And so let's go back and now read what we have here in the text.
So we say that one of the key characteristics of tumor is that it is monoclonal.
So again, one of the key characteristics of neoplasia is that it is monoclonal.
And that means that the neoplastic cells are derived from a single mother cell.
And as I've stated here, clonality can be determined by G6PD isoforms.
Now we could play the exact same game using androgen receptor isoforms, because androgen
receptor isoforms are also on the X chromosome.
And so we could say that the patient has androgen receptor A, androgen receptor B, androgen
receptor C or D or E, etc.
And we could play the exact same game that we played with G6PD.
But this is a fundamental principle of neoplasia.
And that is that all neoplasia, whether it be benign, whether it be malignant, all neoplasia,
all tumors, are monoclonal by definition.
Okay.
Another way that we could play the clonality game is to look at immunoglobulin light chain
phenotype.
And this is a way by which we can determine the clonality of B cells.
This is high yield, and so it's worth taking a moment to understand the concept.
Now let's play the same game, but this time pretend that there is an individual, and we're
looking at their lymph node.
Now let's pretend that this individual's lymph node is made up of four cells.
Okay.
Obviously it's not, but for the purposes of illustration, it makes it easy.
So if the patient actually has four cells in their lymph node, you should recall that the
B cells present within the lymph node express immunoglobulin, and that immunoglobulin is comprised of both
heavy chain and light chain.
Now the light chain for each individual B cell will either be kappa or lambda.
There's only two choices.
Either a B cell expresses kappa or it expresses lambda light chain.
And generally speaking, the ratio of kappa to lambda cells within the lymph node or within
any collection of lymphocytes is three to one.
So that if we had four cells making up this lymph node, three of the cells would express kappa
light chain, and one of the cells would express lambda light chain.
All right.
Now let's pretend that a patient gets an infection.
And when they get an infection, what's going to happen is that they're going to get hyperplasia
of the cells of the lymph node because there's going to be a response to the infection and
the B cells are going to proliferate.
And we know that when we get infections that the lymph nodes become bigger.
And so if the lymph node becomes bigger, we could ask the question, why is the lymph node bigger?
What type of proliferation is occurring?
And if there was an infection and the proliferation was due to hyperplasia, then what we would expect
is that in hyperplasia, each of these cells would contribute because it's polyclonal.
Each of these cells would contribute additional cells.
So for example, if this is a kappa light chain B cell, then each of these cells is making additional cells.
Let's just draw these here.
And each of the additional cells is going to have the same light chain ratio of three to one.
And so, you know, these two would be kappa.
These two would be kappa.
These would be lambda.
And this would be lambda.
And so the ratio here is one, two, three, four, five, six to two, which really is the same three to one ratio
that we would expect to see in a normal lymph node.
And again, that's because the proliferation in hyperplasia is polyclonal.
And so one of the key features of a polyclonal proliferation is that the kappa to lambda ratio of immunoglobulin light chain would remain three to one.
Now, let's take the other extreme, and I'm going to go ahead and erase this.
And let's take another extreme where a patient has a lymph node.
And the lymph node is basically a kappa, you know, three kappas, as we've already explained.
The normal ratio is three to one and one lambda.
And then let's pretend that the patient gets a neoplastic proliferation.
Now, when a patient gets a neoplastic proliferation, i.e. a lymphoma, one cell is going to be making all of the malignant cells.
And so what's going to happen is we're going to get a massive excess of kappa.
And, of course, there will still be some lambdas, but what will happen is that the kappa to lambda ratio, instead of being three to one, will become something like 20 to one.
And this is very high yield, and that's exactly the way the examiners play it.
They tell you that the patient's got an enlarged lymph node.
Okay, when the patient has an enlarged lymph node, what's the differential diagnosis?
Well, there's really only three things that you really think about when you have an enlarged lymph node.
One thing that can enlarge the lymph node is metastatic cancer.
So if a patient has cancer and it spreads to the lymph node, the lymph node becomes bigger.
Another thing that can enlarge the lymph node is reactive hyperplasia, because the patient gets an infection and the lymph node becomes bigger.
And the third thing that can enlarge the lymph node is going to be lymphoma.
Now, let's say that they tell you that the patient has an enlarged lymph node, a biopsy is performed, and it shows a proliferation of lymphocytes.
Then we're thinking, aha, proliferation of lymphocytes, it must be either reactive hyperplasia or lymphoma.
And then they'll tell you on an examination that the light chain is studied and the light chain ratio is 20 to one.
So once you hear that the light chain ratio is 20 to one, you know that you're dealing with a monoclonal proliferation.
And that monoclonal proliferation must then be a lymphoma, because that's really the only tumor that you can get within a lymph node.
So I hope that that's clear because that, again, is also high yield.
So again, here's what I've stated in the book.
In your text, the clonality of B cells is determined by immunoglobulin light chain phenotype.
Okay, now, going back to a general principle, when we have neoplasia, neoplasia can be benign or it can be malignant.
Let me make something very clear, because sometimes this is misunderstood and it's missed on examinations as well.
Both benign tumors or neoplasia and malignant tumors or neoplasia, both of these are monoclonal.
Whether it be a benign tumor or it be a malignant tumor, neoplasia, generally speaking, is monoclonal.
Alright, so I want to highlight that point.
Now, benign tumors, one of the key characteristics of benign tumors is that they tend to remain localized in the tissue in which they grow,
and they absolutely do not metastasize.
That's a key characteristic of benign tumors.
Malignant tumors are also called cancer, and a characteristic of malignant tumors is that they invade locally,
and they have the potential to metastasize.
What do I mean by potential to metastasize?
Meaning that in a subset of patients, those tumors will metastasize, but it doesn't need to metastasize in every single patient.
So, for example, if a woman has breast cancer and it's localized to the breast,
if that cancer has the propensity to metastasize in patients, then we would still call it cancer,
even though it hasn't metastasized in that individual patient.
So, it simply has the potential to metastasize in any given patient.
So, again, this is another general principle concerning neoplasia.
Now, if we go a step further, we can go, and given that we understand that tumors can be benign or malignant,
we should then understand that tumors will have particular lineages of differentiation.
And the way I think about this is, you know, you've got four major tissues within the body.
You've got epithelium, which are the cells that line the surface of the body.
So, they line the skin, they line the gut, they line the esophagus, they line the urogenital tract.
All right, those are epithelial cells.
You've got mesenchyme.
What is mesenchyme?
Mesenchyme is a connective tissue in the body.
So, the mesenchyme includes fat, blood vessels, bone, cartilage, okay?
It's your soft tissue, basically.
Your soft tissue, your bone, your cartilage.
That's mesenchyme.
There are lymphocytes in the body, and then there are melanocytes in the body.
And each of these individual types of cells can develop tumors,
and when they develop tumors, those tumors can be benign or malignant.
So, for example, a benign tumor of epithelium, when it produces glands, is called an adenoma.
And a malignant tumor of epithelium, when it produces glands, is called an adenocarcinoma.
A benign tumor of epithelium, when it creates papillary finger-like structures, is called a papilloma.
And a malignant tumor of epithelium, when it creates papillary finger-like structures, is called a papillary carcinoma.
And what do I mean by papillary finger-like structures?
Well, it basically means that you've got this growth of epithelial cells.
So these are the epithelial cells.
And that they overlie a connective tissue core with a blood vessel in the center.
So there's a connective tissue core with a blood vessel in the center.
And so those are papillary growths.
And papillary growths, when they're benign, they're called papillomas.
When they're malignant, they're called papillary carcinomas.
Mesenchymal tissue can also be benign or can produce tumors that will be benign or malignant.
And it's going to be named based on the type of tissue that it forms.
So lipo means fat, and oma means mass.
So a benign tumor of fat is a lipoma.
And lipo, again, means fat.
And sarcoma means malignant mesenchymal tissue.
And so a malignant tumor of fat would be called a liposarcoma.
And you can play this game with all types of mesenchymal.
For example, osteoma, benign tumor of bone.
Osteosarcoma, malignant tumor of bone.
Chondroma, benign tumor of cartilage.
Chondrosarcoma, malignant tumor of cartilage.
Angioma, benign tumor of blood vessels.
Angiosarcoma, malignant tumor of blood vessels.
Etc.
Okay.
Lymphocytes can also form tumors.
There is no such thing as a benign tumor of lymphocytes.
Anytime you have a neoplastic proliferation of lymphocytes,
it is automatically lymphoma or leukemia.
Alright?
It automatically becomes lymphoma or leukemia.
And melanocytes can also produce tumors.
And we can get benign tumors or malignant tumors.
A benign tumor of melanocytes is called a nevus.
Also commonly called a mole.
And a malignant tumor of melanocytes is called a melanoma.
Again, melanoma referring to the melanocyte.
And oma referring to mass.
And in fact, that was the basis for my naming of the website
that I've put all of these lectures on, Pathoma,
i.e. Massive Pathology Information.
But anyway, that's a separate discussion.
So that's tumor nomenclature.
And we should be familiar with that because we're going to do
a lot of tumor study as we move forward.
And you're going to have to understand the nomenclature.
But we will cover it as we go through the organ systems again.
Now, epidemiology is important to understand.
The examiners like to go after epidemiology.
I think it's important for you to be familiar with a little bit
of epidemiology as you go through your medical training.
And so let's just mention a few important points.
First of all, cancer is the second leading cause of death
in both adults and children.
And it's important to know that, generally speaking,
the major causes of death in adults are, number one,
cardiovascular disease.
So that probably tells you that cardiovascular disease is important
to be familiar with.
You're going to see a ton of it in your careers.
And you're going to see a ton of it on examinations.
Cancer is the second cause of death in adults,
second leading cause of death in adults.
So we should be well aware of cancer,
and we're going to see it commonly.
And the third is cerebrovascular disease.
And so these are the three leading causes of death in adults.
Causes of death in children, number one, accidents.
And accidents, unfortunately, are a cause of death
that can often be avoided but are overlooked.
And so we need to be particularly careful about making sure
that we as physicians, when we have access
to a pediatric population, ensure that patients are particularly
careful with their children.
For example, making sure that children are in car seats
and wear their seat belts, et cetera.
But anyway, accidents are the number one cause
of death in children.
The second leading cause of death in children is cancer.
And the third leading cause of death in children is congenital defects.
Taking the epidemiology one step further,
we can ask ourselves, what are the most common cancers in adults?
Now these types of tables in which the most common cancers in adults
are discussed, basically what you should know is that these exclude skin.
So squamous cell carcinoma and basal cell carcinoma of the skin
are very common tumors.
But we're going to exclude them because although they're malignant,
they rarely metastasize and they're more of a nuisance than anything else.
They quickly reveal themselves because they're on the skin
and they can easily be treated and are rarely,
or are not commonly a cause of death.
And so basically we're going to remove those tumors from the list
and we're going to talk about the most common cancers in adults
by incidence and by mortality.
So the three most common cancers in adults by incidence are,
number one, breast or prostate.
Obviously breast in a female and prostate in a male.
Number two, lung.
That's the second most common cancer by incidence.
And number three, colorectal.
So these are the sort of the most common cancers by incidence.
Now if we were to look at this list by mortality,
by those cancers that actually cause death,
then lung jumps up to number one.
And then breast in a female and prostate in a male is number two.
And colorectal is number three.
And so one of the things that I like to highlight when we look at this list
is notice the change.
Although breast and prostate are the most common,
they don't, they aren't the most common killers.
And instead lung,
although it's less common than breast and prostate,
jumps up to become the number one killer.
And I, and I'd like to, like to highlight that
because it's an important fact to be aware of,
in particular because lung cancer,
the vast majority of it is actually due to smoking.
And this is the one cancer on the list where we exactly,
we have a very, very good idea of what causes it.
And it's a relatively removable cause
because although it might be difficult to stop smoking,
it's something that we could certainly encourage our patients to do.
But what I want to highlight here
is that notice that lung is actually jumping up to number one
as a cause of mortality.
And this sort of brings us to a point that's important to understand.
And that is one of the greatest treatments,
or one of the greatest mechanisms
by which we can actually handle,
handle cancer is early detection.
If we can detect cancer early
and remove it from the patient
before it really can wreak havoc in that patient,
that is one of the greatest ways
by which we can serve our patients
because really the story of cancer is the story of,
sort of the best way by which to deal with a cancer
is to actually detect it either before it becomes a cancer
and then remove it,
or to detect it before it produces clinical symptoms.
And I'm going to highlight that in a moment,
but let's just look at this list again now
from a different perspective.
So when you think about breast,
we have a method of screening for breast, right?
We can do mammogram, we can do physical exam.
Prostate, we have a mechanism for screening for prostate.
Although it's a little bit debated,
we currently screen with PSA and digital rectal exam.
Colorectal, we have a mechanism of screening for colorectal.
We do hemocult testing of the stool
and we also do colonoscopy after a certain age.
So each of these tumors can be caught relatively early.
And because they can be caught relatively early,
we can do a pretty good job of reducing the mortality.
However, in the case of lung cancer,
there is no screening mechanism.
Lung cancer usually presents late in the course.
There is no practical screening methodology.
And so therefore, it pops up to number one
as far as mortality is concerned.
And to me, one of the most interesting statistics is that
if I asked you what was the five-year survival for lung cancer
30 years ago, the answer would be about 15%.
And if I ask you what's the five-year survival for lung cancer today,
the answer is about 15%.
It hasn't changed very much.
There's been a little bit of an increased survival
due to improve surgical technique,
but for the vast majority, basically, generally speaking,
the survival of lung cancer really hasn't improved over the last 30 years.
And that's despite the fact that we've got all these designer drugs
and understanding of molecular biology,
but I think really the underlying principle or premise there is that
we really don't have a practical method to screen for lung cancer,
and hence we're not picking up lung cancer early.
And because we're not picking up lung cancer early,
we catch the cat way after it's out of the bag.
And so, unfortunately, that's the circumstance with lung cancer,
and this is a very important principle that I'm just trying to nail home here.
Now, maybe it'd be a little bit...
It's worth having a discussion of screening for a few reasons.
One is because it's tested, and two, because we have to be familiar with it.
So, it is important to sort of stop and take a step back
and do a little discussion here on screening.
So, let me just remind you that basically the idea in cancer is that you've got one cell,
okay, and that one cell gets mutated.
And that one cell, once it becomes mutated, it's then going to produce a cancer.
And this one cell will become two cells, and two cells will become four cells,
and four cells will become eight cells, until eventually what happens is you produce a cancer
in which clinical symptoms arise, okay?
And so, one of the things that examiners like you to know is how many divisions have to occur
before the average tumor reveals clinical symptoms.
And the answer is that there are about 30 divisions that will occur
before the earliest clinical symptoms arise in cancer.
So, that's one important point.
And that's what I've stated here.
Cancer begins as a single mutated cell, and then there's about 30 divisions
before the earliest clinical symptoms arise.
Now, what's important to note is every time a cancer divides, all right,
with every division, there's going to be increased mutations
because cancers are growing out of control.
And so, the DNA is not being repaired, mutations are being picked up,
checked systems are basically not able to control the cell.
And so, with every single division, there's going to be increased mutations.
And so, one important principle or general idea is that if you have a cancer
that doesn't produce symptoms until very late in the disease,
it will have undergone additional mutations, sorry,
it will have undergone additional divisions which will then lead to additional mutations.
And so, whereas the average tumor or the tumor that reveals the earliest clinical symptoms
will have divided 30 times and will then be detected,
there are some tumors that really get detected very late.
For example, ovarian carcinoma.
The ovary has a large area to grow before any clinical symptoms arise,
and because those clinical symptoms are not seen,
and because clinical symptoms are not produced until very late,
sometimes those tumors can grow and extend far beyond these 30 divisions,
and every time they divide, they're picking up mutations.
And so, ovarian carcinoma, generally speaking, has a pretty poor prognosis.
Similarly, with pancreatic carcinoma.
Pancreatic carcinoma, the pancreas has a large space to grow before clinical symptoms arise.
The pancreas has a large reserve before the tissue damage can reveal itself,
and so pancreatic carcinoma has a horrible prognosis.
And same thing with lung cancer.
The lung has a tremendous reserve,
and a cancer can grow significantly before clinical symptoms actually arise.
And so, these tumors will tend to have a worse prognosis.
And that's what I've basically stated here,
that cancers that are detected late, they tend to have a poor prognosis.
All right, so that's important to know.
Now, what's the goal of screening?
Now, remember that I told you that tumor develops from a single cell,
and that single cell becomes two cells, which becomes four cells,
which becomes eight cells, which eventually produces clinical symptoms, right?
And every time these divisions occur, there's going to be an increase in mutations.
Okay?
So, what is the goal of screening?
Screening has two separate goals.
The first goal is to catch dysplasia before it becomes cancer,
i.e. even before this cell is present,
we try to catch dysplasia so that we don't even have to deal with the formation of a cancer.
What's an example?
Well, when we do pap smear.
When we do a pap smear, we're looking for cervical intraepithelial neoplasia,
with CIN1, CIN2, CIN3.
And what is CIN?
CIN is basically dysplasia.
It's not cancer.
It is dysplasia.
Now, it has a risk of developing into cancer,
and so what we do is, when we have CIN, we remove the CIN,
we remove the epithelium of the cervix before it can actually become cancer.
And just note that the difference between dysplasia and cancer is that dysplasia has mutations,
but it's reversible.
But cancer has mutations, and it's irreversible,
and it's growing in an unregulated manner.
Okay?
So, that's one goal of screening.
It's to catch dysplasia before it becomes carcinoma.
Another goal of screening, a separate goal of screening,
is to detect carcinoma before clinical symptoms arise.
So, if this is the cancer, and it's one cell, and it's going to divide into two,
and then four, and then eight, and eventually produce clinical symptoms,
what we'd like to do in screening is, rather than catching the tumor after it produces clinical symptoms,
we might want to catch the tumor earlier before it produces clinical symptoms,
and that would be a goal of screening.
And again, the idea is, if we catch the tumor here before it produces clinical symptoms,
we will have caught the tumor before additional mutations would be allowed to form.
And again, the more the mutations, the more aggressive the tumor would actually be.
So, these are the two goals of screening, and this basically comes into play in many different examples.
For example, as I told you, what's the goal of the pap smear?
The goal of the pap smear is to pick up cervical intraepithelial neoplasia,
whether it be CIN1, CIN2, or CIN3.
And the idea here is that if we pick up CIN before it becomes carcinoma,
we will have eliminated the possibility of carcinoma developing by removing the dysplastic cells.
Alright, so that's the goal of the pap smear.
What's the goal of mammography?
Well, the goal of mammography is to pick up breast cancer
before it actually would produce clinical symptoms.
So, actually, there's kind of two goals of mammography.
The goal is to pick up ductal carcinoma in situ.
What's ductal carcinoma in situ?
That ductal carcinoma in situ is a malignant proliferation of ductal cells that grows in a duct.
Alright, and the goal is to pick up ductal carcinoma in situ before these tumor cells invade,
because once tumor cells invade, they now have access to the blood vessels and the lymphatic spaces,
and there's a propensity for those tumor cells to spread.
The more a tumor spreads, the worse the patient will actually do.
And so one goal of mammography is to pick up ductal carcinoma in situ,
and the idea here is that ductal carcinoma in situ, it calcifies often.
And so mammograms will look for calcification running within ducts,
and that's an indication that the patient may have DCIS or ductal carcinoma in situ.
So that's one goal of mammography.
What's another goal of mammography?
Another goal of mammography is that if this is the patient's breast,
generally speaking, clinically, the average clinically detected tumor,
or tumor that's detected by a patient, the average size is 2 centimeters.
So that's pretty big.
However, if a patient undergoes mammography,
the average size of detection in mammography is 1 centimeter.
So we can pick up tumors that are 1 centimeter by mammography
that we wouldn't be able to pick up until they became 2 centimeters clinically.
All right?
And so mammography allows us to detect a tumor that's half the size of that
which would have normally been detected.
And of course, the larger the tumor, the increase the risk of mutations.
And generally speaking, it's known that the larger the tumor,
the more likely it is to have spread to local lymph nodes or outside of the breast.
And so mammography becomes an important mechanism of screening for cancer.
Another important screening test that we can use is PSA and digital rectal exam.
Now what's the idea here?
The idea here is that, recall that if this is the prostate,
and running through the center of the prostate is the urethra,
the prostate cancer tends to grow in the posterior peripheral aspect of the prostate.
And so it's a relatively silent disease because it doesn't really produce urinary symptoms.
Now, the urethra runs through the center of the prostate.
Do you know what disease process involves the center of the prostate?
Very good, BPH.
BPH involves the center of the prostate.
And BPH will compress the urethra and produce urinary symptoms.
However, prostate cancer tends to grow in the posterior periphery of the prostate
and does not compress the urethra until very late in disease.
And so it's a clinically silent disease.
And so what we'd like to do is pick up these prostate cancers when they're small
and when they have yet to spread throughout most of the prostate or outside of the prostate.
And the way by which we can detect them is an increase in PSA or a digital rectal exam.
Now, how does the digital rectal exam pick up prostate cancer?
Well, recall that prostate cancer occurs in the posterior periphery of the prostate
and running light right along the posterior periphery of the prostate is the rectum.
And so in digital rectal exam, we get a chance to palpate the posterior periphery of the prostate
which is exactly where prostate cancer most commonly develops.
So this is another example of a screening test.
And the final example that I'd like to give is the hemocult test in colonoscopy
for detection of colonic adenomas and colonic carcinoma.
Now the idea here is that recall that colonic carcinoma, adenocarcinoma of the colon,
the vast majority of adenocarcinoma of the colon actually develops from adenomas.
And this is something called the adenoma carcinoma sequence.
We'll discuss the adenoma carcinoma sequence in more detail when we do the
colon lecture.
However, what I'd like to highlight here is that when a patient undergoes colonoscopy,
the goal is to remove the adenomas.
And if we remove the adenomas, then obviously they wouldn't be able to become carcinoma.
And so that's one benefit of colonoscopy.
Another benefit of colonoscopy is if the patient happens to have a cancer,
we hope to catch the cancer before clinical symptoms are found.
And the same with the hemocult test.
The hemocult test has the ability to detect occult blood within the stool.
And that occult blood could be indicative of a large adenoma,
or it could be indicative of a carcinoma.
And so we want to catch adenomas before they become carcinoma,
or we'd like to catch carcinoma before it actually produces clinical symptoms.
So these are some important examples of mechanisms of screening.
And hopefully by now you've got the general idea in your mind of the benefits of screening.
And that really closes off this very introductory discussion of neoplasia.
Much of what I said is high yield.
Much of what I said is going to apply to the organ systems,
the particular organ systems in which they would normally be discussed.
For example, colonoscopy, PSA, digital rectal exam, et cetera.
But what we'll do here is take a moment to, we'll stop here,
give you some time to digest the material,
and when you're ready we can continue with the discussion of carcinogenesis.
Sometimes we'll reduce them in the developing phenomena.
However, the ones that reward them in the protection of carcinogenesis
are important.